<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My journey from Data Analyst to Data Science</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on My journey from Data Analyst to Data Science</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 21:17:58 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Jupyter Notebooks: Boost your productivity with Extensions and Magic Commands</title>
      <link>/2020/07/12/jupyter-notebooks-boost-your-productivity-with-extensions-and-magic-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 21:17:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/12/jupyter-notebooks-boost-your-productivity-with-extensions-and-magic-commands/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How the Inverted Index and Scoring Work in ElasticSearch</title>
      <link>/2020/06/24/how-the-inverted-index-and-scoring-work-in-elasticsearch/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 08:05:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/24/how-the-inverted-index-and-scoring-work-in-elasticsearch/</guid>
      <description>Searching through full text fields with regexes in relational database systems like PostgreSQL or MySQL is painful: The query latency is high and your results will be unordered, so you have no idea how relevant your query results are. Elasticsearch is often the storage engine of choice for storing and querying full text data. In ElasticSearch querying fulltext fields is among the least resource intensive tasks and your query results are ordered putting the most relevant results on top.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working with Complex Datatypes in Hive</title>
      <link>/2020/06/07/working-with-complex-datatypes-in-hive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 08:29:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/06/07/working-with-complex-datatypes-in-hive/</guid>
      <description>table { width:80% !important;}  The basic idea of complex datatypes is to store multiple values in a single column. So if you are working with a Hive database and you query a column, but then you notice &amp;ldquo;This value I need is trapped in a column among other values&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; you just came across a complex a.k.a. nested datatype.
There are three types: arrays, maps and structs. First, you have to understand, which types are present.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mastering Data Preparation with Pandas: Subetting, Filtering and Joining DataFrames</title>
      <link>/2019/08/18/mastering-data-preparation-with-pandas-subetting-filtering-and-joining-dataframes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2019 10:55:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/08/18/mastering-data-preparation-with-pandas-subetting-filtering-and-joining-dataframes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Everything You Need to Know to Use Git for Version Control</title>
      <link>/2018/12/17/everything-you-need-to-know-to-use-git-for-version-control/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 21:17:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/17/everything-you-need-to-know-to-use-git-for-version-control/</guid>
      <description>So many people have recommended Git as a version control system to me. I had a look at it, but I was pretty overwhelmed. Since I did not have a technical background, everything seemed so complex! Many tutorials let me copy paste code without giving you a deeper understanding of what and why I am actually doing this. This copy pasting feels like success at first, but when I tried working with it, I could not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automatically changing the R working directory on Mac OS to source file location</title>
      <link>/2018/12/07/changing-working-directories/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/12/07/changing-working-directories/</guid>
      <description>This post is about how to change your R working directory. You might be wondering:
Why would I want to do that? You need this as soon as your script interacts with folders on your computer. For example for imports or exports of data or figures. So probably almost always. Let&#39;s say you have a script that creates plots and saves them in the folder &amp;quot;Plots&amp;quot;, which is located in your source file directory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formatting tables in R Markdown with kableExtra</title>
      <link>/2018/11/05/formatting-tables-in-r-markdown-with-kableextra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/05/formatting-tables-in-r-markdown-with-kableextra/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I will show you some of my best practises for formatting tables in R Markdown. We will cover
How to generally format tables (font, size, color... )
 How to create tables with conditional formating (e.g. coloring values &amp;lt; 0 red)
  The basics: the R package kableExtra kableExtra is an awesome package that allows you to format and style your tables. It works similar to ggplot2: You create a base table and then add formating layers with the pipe operator %&amp;gt;%.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Markdown for Novices: All you need to know to get started</title>
      <link>/2018/11/03/r-markdown-for-novices-all-you-need-to-know-to-get-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/11/03/r-markdown-for-novices-all-you-need-to-know-to-get-started/</guid>
      <description>I write this blogpost for someone, who has never worked with R Markdown. After you read this post, you will
understand why R Markdown may be useful for your daily work as a student, researcher, analyst or data scientist.
 understand the basic structure of an R Markdown document and how you can get startet.
  I strongly encourage everybody working with R to use R Markdown. I promise, it will make your life so much easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>The theme of this blog was forked from @jrutheiser/hugo-lithium-theme and modified by Yihui Xie.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>